ILGWU. Wilbur Daniels papers, 5780/113
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Wilbur Daniels papers
1967-1973.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wilbur Daniels, 1923-
5780/113
2 cubic feet
2 linear feet
Records
Contains files maintained by Wilbur Daniels while working as Associate General Counsel in the Legal Department, Assistant to the President, Director of the Master Agreements Department, Vice President, and Executive Vice-President. The bulk of the files pertain to the negotiation of agreements with companies and associations in the 1960s and 1970s.
5516344
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
June 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, June 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
Wilbur Daniels was born in Detroit in 1922. Daniels held several offices in the ILGWU over more than 40 years, including Research Association and Assistant Director of Research (1943-1950), Associate General Counsel in the Legal Department (1950-1959), Assistant to the President (1959-1961), Director of the Master Agreements Department (1965-1969?), Vice President (1969-1973), and Executive Vice-President (1973-1987). After leaving the ILGWU in 1987, Daniels was Executive Director of the S.H. and Helen R. Scheuer Foundation. He remained involved in New York City civic life, serving on the boards of the Lincoln Center, United Housing Foundation, New York Urban Coalition, and American Arbitration Association. He died in New York City in 1993.
Scope and Contents
Contains files maintained by Wilbur Daniels while working as Associate General Counsel in the Legal Department, Assistant to the President, Director of the Master Agreements Department, Vice President, and Executive Vice-President. The bulk of the files pertain to the negotiation of agreements with companies and associations in the 1960s and 1970s.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
5780/084. ILGWU. Wilbur Daniels papers
5780/155. ILGWU. Wilbur Daniels papers
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Daniels, Wilbur,1923-; Daniels, Wilbur, 1923-; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5516344
- Associated Sportswear (Majestic Specialties): 1967-1971 [folder 1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Associated Sportswear (Majestic Specialties): 1967-1971 [folder 2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Associated Corset and Brassiere: Out-of-Town, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Corset and Brassiere Out-of-Town Negotiations [folder 1 of 2], 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Corset and Brassiere Out-of-Town Negotiations [folder 2 of 2], 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents
  Yiddish
- Joyce, Andrea, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Associated Sportswear: Ridgefield Plant, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clipping, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Associated Sportswear Company Canton: Supplement Signed, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Associated Sportswear Canton: Supplement, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Associated Sportswear Kelita: Supplement Signed, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Atlantic Apparel, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Associated Sportswear Supplement: Westland Manufacturing, Moreland Sportswear, Charland Sportswear, 1970- 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bali-Hialeah, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Berkshire Apparel: Negotiations [folder 1 of 2], 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Berkshire Apparel: Negotiations [folder 2 of 2], 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Barbizon Corporation: Dubinsky File, 1953-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Barbizon Corporation, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Barbizon Corporation: Working Papers, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Bobbie Brooks Incorporated: Knitwear, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Bobbie Brooks Incorporated, Washington Garment Company, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bobbie Brooks Incorporated, Stretchini Incorporated, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Bobbie Brooks Incorporated: Stacy Ames, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Stretchini Incorporated, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Imports: Speeches [folder 1 of 2], 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Imports: Speeches [folder 2 of 2], 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- General Executive Board Committee (Box 2, Folder 3)
- New York State Association of Settlement Houses, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Wilbur Daniels, 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Roger Webb: NCUC, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- New York Dress: Negotiations, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- New York Salute to the Fashion Industry, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Education, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- General Executive Board, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Multifiber Arrangement (Box 2, Folder 11)
- National Consumer Cooperative Bank, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Apparel Jobs Training Corporation, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Apparel Jobs Research Corporation, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Green-Dolmatch Incorporated, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Advertising, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Apparel Job Training and Research Corporation, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Appeal Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Cardio Pulmonary Resuscitation, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Unemployment Insurance, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Wage Controls, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Unity House, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Koret, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Labor Management Cooperation, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Office and Professional Employs International Union, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Indochinese Refugees, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Homework, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Malden Mills Incorporated, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Malden Mills Incorporated: 1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Shop Chairperson's Manual, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Trade Adjustment Assistance, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  October 19, 1978
- Unemployment Insurance, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Mediation and Termination Notices, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Master Agreements (Firms), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 35)